<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new discovery of the horrid association &amp; conspiracy of the papists in Lancashire to raise war and rebellion in the kingdom of England, during the absence of King William in Ireland. : In a letter of instructions from a Roman Catholick of great quality, in London, to a papist mutineer in Lancashire.</title>
            <author>Greenwood, Jonathan.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03555</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">49520890</idno>
  <idno type="VID">174132</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240883725</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G36</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222927</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">49520890</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03555)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174132)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2666:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new discovery of the horrid association &amp; conspiracy of the papists in Lancashire to raise war and rebellion in the kingdom of England, during the absence of King William in Ireland. : In a letter of instructions from a Roman Catholick of great quality, in London, to a papist mutineer in Lancashire.</title>
                  <author>Greenwood, Jonathan.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Greenwood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: J.G. [i.e. Jonathan Greenwood].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Lancashire Plot, 1689-1694 --  Sources.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:174132:1"/>
            <p>A NEW DISCOVERY Of the Horrid Association &amp; Conspiracy OF THE PAPISTS in <hi>Lancashire,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174132:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174132:2"/>
            <p>A <hi>New Discovery</hi> Of the Horrid Association &amp; Conspiracy OF THE PAPISTS in <hi>Lancashire:</hi> TO Raise War and Rebellion in the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> during the Absence of King <hi>William</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> In a Letter of Instructions from a <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> of Great Quality, in <hi>London,</hi> to a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist Mutineer</hi> in <hi>Lancashire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Greenwood,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:174132:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174132:3"/>
            <head>A NEW DISCOVERY Of the Horrid Association &amp; Conspiracy OF THE PAPISTS in <hi>Lancashire,</hi> &amp;c. Instructions sent from a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> of Great Quality in <hi>London,</hi> to his Friend a <hi>Papist Mutineer</hi> in <hi>Lancashire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THOUGH I can with abundance of good Will, and all the love and liking of a true Son of our Holy <hi>Mother Church,</hi> applaud your Zeal for the Service of our reputed <hi>Declining Cause;</hi> yet I must freely ask leave to censure your Discretion, and arraign your Judgment for so unseasonable Applications of Wrath and Revenge, at a time when by the unexpected gentle
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174132:4"/> Usage of our <hi>Prevailing Adversaries</hi> we are obliged in Honour, Conscience and Duty to acquiesce in at least, if not to approve the mild Proceedings of so justly a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked Government: For to be plain, though the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of Heresie by the just Enjoynder of our Church, is and ought to be by every of her Members, with all just Zeal and Industry prosecuted and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, yet I could never arrive to those Heights which some of our high-flown Brethren so warmly maintain, <hi>viz.</hi> Of endeavouring to raise the Credit of our Church and Religion, by the Loss and Destruction of all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Principles of Morality and Vertue.</p>
            <p>And although it be certain that too many of our Pastors indulge and promote our Belief, That the greatest Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is as it were sanctified by the Agents Intention of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to our Church; yet I must be bold to own, That I cannot more admire and reverence the Purity of our Holy Religion; than detest and abhor the Baseness of such a Principle that is utterly destructive to all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, the Bane of Kings, and Snare to Subjects; that ties up the Hands of Charity, and bids Defiance to all Godliness; a Principle, to the unfortunate Practice whereof we owe the Growth of Schism, the Contempt of our Clergy, and our present Fears and suppos'd Dangers. And lastly, A Principle which we must with shame confess foisted into our Church by a Sect of Men amongst us, whose Ambition, Cruelty and Covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness has even from the Life of their first Founder for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited all Pretensions to the Purity of their Title, and whose violent wicked Conduct has been at all times the Plague, and now (at last in <hi>England</hi>) I fear the utter Ruine and Destruction of our Cause and Profession.</p>
            <p>This being premis'd, I shall endeavour to convince you of the unreasonableness of your Endeavours to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174132:4"/> raise War and <hi>Rebellion</hi> (for so I must name it) from these Three Considerations, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>First, From the Ingratitude of such an Action.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, From the very little, or really no probability of Success.</item>
                  <item>And Lastly, From the dreadful Consequences of such an Attempt, supposing you should fail in it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>First then, If you will believe the practice of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vertues not incompatible with the exercise of our holy Religion; you must confess there are many grateful Returns due to a Prince, who by so many gracious Condescentions to his sworn actual Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, even after the highest and bitterest Provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, has so recommended himself to the good Opinions of the better part of the Christian World, as to be look'd upon as the Standard of Honour, Vertue and Courtisie in all the Courts of <hi>Europe;</hi> his long Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Affronts and Injuries of the severest nature, even from a Father and Unkle, I can let alone, with much more VVill than Justice, and rejoyce much more at the opportunity of passing them over in silence, than be put to the necessity of a Blush in the repetition; his Father's siding with his greatest Enemy in the robbing and detaining his rightful Inheritance, without the least Plea of Law and Justice; his endeavouring to make him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to the Subversion of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> and consequently of rendring him odious or suspected to to those who in all probability were shortly to be his Subjects. And lastly, his unimitable Design to set up a Spurious Issue to dis-inherit the Princess and himself.</p>
            <p>All these Designs, I say, which by the sole Counsel and abetting of Jesuits and Papists, (as it was too sensibly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174132:5"/> believ'd at least) were Provocations, which without a mixture of Divinity in his Nature, no Mortal could with the least moderation bear, and the least of which, believe me, our beloved Monarch would with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most art of Revenge, and the most exquisite Tortures, have retaliated; but quite otherwise, when by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>disputable Fortune of Arms, by his greatest seeming In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests, by the natural Appetite and desire of Revenge we saw it in his Power, and had the greatest reason in the World to fear his just Resolutions to destroy us; even then I say, we saw him survey us with the Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of a Lamb, with the Mercy of a Saviour, and the Generosity of an Hero; and further, that even since his Establishment, there has not, nor in any likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood will there one Person suffer Death, among the many notorious Malefactors, (as the Law of <hi>England</hi> calls them) of the two last Reigns.</p>
            <p>Consider this, Dear Sir, and think how inhumanly black even in Catholick Countries we shall appear, if after such unspeakable Grace and Goodness, we shall so much as attempt any thing against your Interests, or fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ishly trouble our selves concerning the Pretensions of our so <hi>great Benefactor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You cannot be insensible, if you will take the pains seriously to reflect in your Heart, that our Condition in reality is now more advantagious and satisfactory, than at any time it has been since their Separation from, and renunciation of the Jurisdiction of our most <hi>Holy Father the Pope:</hi> For though by the Connivance and Indulgence of our late Gracious Sovereign K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. and by the Endeavours of his Royal Brother King <hi>James</hi> the Second, we began to <hi>see the Sun of Hope break clearly out upon us,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:174132:5"/> and although by the Power and Authority of each of them, we saw our Selves not only toleratedin the open Profession and Practice of our Holy Religion; but also set up Candidates, nay, and actually promoted to places of the greatest Honour and Profit in the Kingdom; <hi>Yet between you and I,</hi> I must conscientiously own, that those Favours, though highly to our Interest, were yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd directly against the plain Letter of many positive Laws amongst them, and consequently, that the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them, accompanied with the continual Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs, and many times open Exclamations (which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity alone, we find was to ripen into actual Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance and Non-complyance) was, and in my Opinion is much less satisfactory to us than the moderate, but voluntary and legal Toleration, at least connivance, which we under the present Government enjoy, and which if we behave our Selves now like Prudent Men, meek and good Christians, true English Men, and Loyal Subjects, we need not doubt to see established upon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, surer, and more lasting Foundations than by all the Fraud, Illegality, and Force we lately made use of (at least as they alledge) could ever be expected or pretended: A considering Man with half an Eye might have seen, and judg'd of the Issue of the violent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the last Reign; and though the Ambition and Covetousness of an ill natured Party of Men amongst us, (on whom I have before hinted) who were ever more Famous for the Boldness of their Attempts, than the Success of their Prosecutions, by their crafty Insinuations, blinded us into a belief of the feasibleness of their Designs; yet a small inspection into the fix'd Nature of the English in general, would have serv'd for a sufficient discouragement to the precipitate Counsels of those hot headed Policians.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:174132:6"/>
            <p>Liberty and Property are so much the Darlings of the English Nation, that a Man might with more ease, and better assurance, make an attempt on the Golden Apples of the <hi>Hesperian Garden,</hi> than offer at a publick Encroachment on them; and the ever-waking Dragon could not be more industrious to preserve the one, than the Patriots and People of <hi>England</hi> are to defend the other.</p>
            <p>Now that publick Attempts and Encroachments were made on the Premisses aforesaid, the Breach of most of the Laws made for above a Century of Years in relation to us and them, they say, do very plainly evince (I take a Liberty with you, which perhaps others of our Religious would give me but very little Thanks for; but believe me, all I say is too true) nor will our Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection salve the Matter, <hi>viz.</hi> That supposing all Things were unravell'd, and brought in the same Ballance as they were before their pretended Reformation, it were but Justice, Conscience and Reason, and which every good Catholick ought with his utmost endeavour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry to prosecute and obtain; to this I answer, that the change of affairs in Church and State that was begun in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's time, was consented to, and enacted by the consent and free voluntary advice of the whole Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> by their representatives in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that the Laws and Penal Severities made since in the several Reigns of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, Q. <hi>Elizabath,</hi> King <hi>Jac. Car.</hi> 1st, <hi>Car.</hi> 2d, were not against Papists as meerly Papists, but as Mutineers, Rebels, Plotters; so that we must really and in all Justice and conscience lay the sanction of most of the Sanguinary and Penal Laws at the doors of our degenerated Brethren, who by their Rebellious Practices, Horrible Contrivances, and Bloody Actions, have justly render'd themselves obnoxious to the best of Governments.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:174132:6"/>
            <p>I press this discourse to you, Dear Friend, with a little more warmth than to you may seem suitable or seasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, even though granted for truth; but I protest to you upon my Honour and Conscience, that I mean no more by it than by a real and just representation of things to you, I may disingage you from such pernicious Principles which are too often to my own knowledge slurr'd upon us by ignorant, selfish, hot-headed Men, the generality of the Professours of our most holy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Faith, from the imputations of Blood, Cruelty, Perfidiousness, which by the reiterated Practices of Villains, are too truly, though very hardly laid to the charge of them all.</p>
            <p>And lastly, as your real Friend to disswade you from the least concurring, abetting, aiding or assisting in that damnable though foolish Association in your own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try or elsewhere, to rise in Rebellion to cause any riots or disorders during King <hi>William</hi>'s absence, by stirring up Arms, or by inciting any of your Friends to any the like designs. For besides that as I told you already, such practices more especially at this time, are inconsistent with honour, conscience, and especially gratitude due to the benigne and generous Disposition of so gracious a Prince from us all: You must in the Second place con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the little or no probability you have to succeed, if you should be so vain to engage in such an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise.</p>
            <p>Our Three great Pillars whereon we supinely lean, are, I presume, the assistance of <hi>France,</hi> the Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Malecontents in <hi>England;</hi> all meer Chimaeras, Clouds that in my Conscience this only Summers Sun will dissipate and drive away.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:174132:7"/>
            <p>For <hi>First,</hi> As to <hi>France,</hi> the Assistance that we can expect from thence, must be by one, or all of these three Methods, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, By sending into <hi>Ireland</hi> considerable Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of Men and Mony, and all other necessary Provisions of War, and almost all Necessaries for Life.</p>
            <p>Or Secondly, By giving King <hi>William</hi> a diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of his Arms in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by making a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Descent upon <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or Lastly, By patching up a Peace upon any Terms with the Confederates, that so he may apply his whole Strength against <hi>England,</hi> and so force them to a re-acceptance of King <hi>James</hi> into his Throne again.</p>
            <p>These are the three Proposals, that on that side we comfort and buoy our selves up with; but which to a Protestant, who maintains that Miracles are ceas'd, are the most improbable, vain and fictitious Stories as ever were utter'd or imagin'd, and which upon any considerate Man's Enquiry and Consideration, will appear ridiculous even to Ideotism.</p>
            <p>For First, Let us only reflect on what he has done, and from thence we may undoubtedly be able to give a shrewd Guess at what he is, or will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174132:7"/> be able to do for the effectual re-instating of King <hi>James.</hi> We all know that <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French King,</hi> is by all the Sacred Ties of Honour, Gratitude, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, and above all, of Interest, obliged to stand by King <hi>James,</hi> and to endeavour by any means to see that Person set at the Helm of the Government of <hi>England</hi> again, who by a fatal Bigotry to his Friendship, had first chalk'd him out a Path that led to the performance of all his ambitious Usurpations. This I say was so plainly incumbent on him for the several Reasons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, that even the Dolthead of an Irish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man has been able to see through it, and expect assistance for the bringing it about, far greater than the aforesaid renown'd Hero has been either able or willing to afford: For granting the assistance of Six thousand Men, which even by their own Accounts, want a thousand or two of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; I cannot but look on it very insignificant to the maintaining of a Kingdom, which by the united Force of <hi>England</hi> is resolv'd upon to be reduced: To this add, That the Forces sent from <hi>France</hi> were so little capable to be spar'd, that he was forc'd to desire the like number, or more to be return'd in their places; from whence na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ariseth this Consideration, That either he has no Men of his own to spare, or that the Irish are not in themselves capable of maintaining the Country; If he has not Men to spare, Where is the mighty assistance we rely upon, and expect thence? If he has, Why do's he not deal more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174132:8"/> sincerely and effectually for the restoration of the King? And then if the numerous boasted Army of the Irish are not able to drive their Adversaries out; how small an addition of help will four or five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Men contribute against so powerful, enrag'd and resolute Army as will certainly meet them? Then for the Warlike Ammunition, Provision, Mony, and other necessaries, the Supplies have been so very inconsiderable, that the Irish them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, though naturally boasting and magnifying their Circumstances, have been asham'd almost to own any; so mightily are these Mountains of Gold, from <hi>France,</hi> dwindled into Mole-Hills, of Hypocrysy, Perjury, Self-Interest, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For believe me, my Friend, <hi>Lewis</hi> the French King has in the somenting the War of <hi>Ireland,</hi> no other hopes, aim, or indeed probability of Success, than by getting the strongest Fortresses of the Kingdom into his Hands, to make himself able to drill off for a time the powerful Application of the Arms of <hi>England</hi> from his own Dominions, and retains not in reality, so much as a grateful remembrance of the Services of K. <hi>James</hi> to him, nor of assisting or supporting his Pretensions, than under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text to make him a necessary Instrument for the furtherance of his Interest: What shall I say of the insupportable Insolencies, and haughty Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of those few French, not only to the Irish, whom they ought to look upon as Friends and Allies, but even to the King himself, I need not mention; the several peremptory Denials of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174132:8"/> his Orders and Commands, the Haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiness, and I may justly say Impudence of that little crooked Vermine, Monsieur <hi>Lazune</hi> the French Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, is such as has made it become a By-Word throughout the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and render'd the King the very scorn and laughing-stock of his Enemies, and the pity of all others that hear it; Tell me my Friend, would it not make the Heart of an English-man tingle, when he is told that the King of <hi>England</hi> is not suffered to dispense even Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Justice to his Subjects, without the Licence of a French Puny General? Oh let the sacred Sense of Loyalty and Duty restrain my rising Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, lest I undutifully break out into Reproaches of so poor, precarious, degenerate, <hi>descending Majesty;</hi> and yet this is sincerely true, that neither the Motion of any part of the Army, the Process or Execution of a Malefactor, nor hardly the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposal of a Commission, or place of Trust, is in the power of K. <hi>James,</hi> before Approbation and Consent first had of Monsieur <hi>Lazune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From Hence naturally arise hard Words, Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies and Fears between the French and the Irish, who, though a People of the thickest Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion in Europe, yet cannot but be provoked by such plain gross Impositions; and an Army at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance in it self, will very little need a Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cler to expatiate upon the Fame of their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:174132:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:174132:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:174132:10"/>
            <p>From hence I fancy you may draw a just esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of all the boasted assistance <hi>France</hi> is able to afford towards the Restoration of K. <hi>James</hi> by any Furniture of Men, Mony, Provision or Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition for the bringing the War in <hi>Ireland</hi> to its wish'd perfection. We will now take a short View of what may be expected from him, upon the aforesaid Considerations, if he should happily venture to make an Attempt upon <hi>England</hi> during the King's Absence.</p>
            <p>In the handling of this Point, I know you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect I should grant you, that the <hi>French King</hi> is at this time the most powerful Monarch in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom; a Concession which if you will take as comparatively with any other one Prince, perhaps I should not quarrel with you about; but if you will needs flatter your self with an Exaltation of his Strength and Might above the United Forces of all the Confederates, I must be plain to tell you, that any knowing Man can never be a Proselyte to such an Opinion or Belief: Nay, I am so very far from my Assent in that matter, that though I know he has by the irreparable Damage of his own Subjects, by the ruine of many worthy and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Princes his Neighbours, by the Desolation and Destruction of many fair populous Countries, by and infinite Effusion of innocent Christian Blood: And lastly, by a long and altogether
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174132:10"/> causless disturbance of the Peace of <hi>Christendom,</hi> lull'd himself in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fantastick dream of an Universal Empire; yet you and I and all must be sensible that he owes the extent of his Dominions, the exorbitancy of his Power and the very foundation of all his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to the unhappy connivance (not to give it a worse name) of our Two last Kings. You cannot I say be insensible that if either King <hi>Charles</hi> or King <hi>James</hi> had at any time resolved upon a Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with <hi>France,</hi> and had disengaged themselves from that myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Association with him (which by the vilest Acts and practices he perswaded them into) they had quickly been able to put a stop to his aspiring greatness; and made the haughty genius of <hi>Franee</hi> shrink back and quietly contain it self within its proper limits, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless I would not have you from my seeming acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his present greatness conclude upon a certainty, or so much as a probability of his being able to make a descent upon <hi>England,</hi> no, not even in this juncture, for although we may flatter our selves with the feasibleness of the project; by recounting the many helps they would meet with from the inclinations abundance of us have to joyn and assist them, yet the obstructions and difficulties to accomplish any thing of Moment to me, seem so inextricable that though I had never so much will I could hardly be brought on to think of any engaging in so mad a design: That four parts of five of the English Nation are cordially affected to the present settlement of the Nation, I beleive may be easily demonstrated; and that the English in general were ever implacable Enemies to the French, has on an hundred occasions been evinced.</p>
            <p>Now from these few Considerations it seems to me impractica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the French to pretend to make a Descent upon <hi>England;</hi> and if ever you hope to make me an Abettor of your projects, you must first convince me of the possibility of their success: I presume you will allow double the number for a Descent upon <hi>England</hi> as was allow'd to <hi>Ireland,</hi> which amounting to ten or twelve thousand (almost the quantity that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> brought with him) will require greater preparations than perhaps the French King will ever be able or willing to advance upon so ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous an occasion, for beside the almost inevitable danger from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174132:11"/> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>utch and our Fleets, whose good inclinations to attempts of that nature (though upon the greatest disadvantage imaginable) he has too well and lately experimented, I can never believe that he would hazard the lives of ten Thousand of his best men (for such they must be if he has the least hope of succeeding) to the fury of an already alarm'd Countrey, and all upon the poor assurance of an inconsiderable number of men of small quality, less ability, and of no reputation or credit: for granting that in every County of <hi>England</hi> there were two or three hundred persons associated (which is altogether incredible, and indeed hardly possible) you cannot possibly draw together, to any the least considerable body before the very Militia will snap you up, and believe me Sir, King <hi>William</hi> has so well the Art of keeping as well as gaining a Crown, that none but madmen can believe he would leave the Kingdom ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to such wretched attempts as these, and for your <hi>French</hi> I know no readier way upon Earth, to unite the people of <hi>England</hi> to a general opposition as the project you so much please your self with: Well but rather than fail of performance (for I am sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible how much your wise Politicians hate to be baulk'd) you will have a Peace with the Confederates ready cut and dry'd, that so you may have <hi>France</hi> at Liberty to set upon us on all sides, and as it were swallow us up at a mouthful. Well now, this a body would think should without dispute or scruple work its desired effect upon us, and yet upon one serious thought of a considerate man he would think us much fitter to be begg'd for Fools than hang'd for Rebels, if we should be so mad as to attempt an Insurrection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on so miserably wretched an Incouragement.</p>
            <p>For first as there is not the least probability, thought or word of a Peace as yet at least, and consequently that you missing the expected assistance may be all taken, hang'd and rotten before such a thing can be brought about, so can any thing but an Idiot or will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blind man beleive that granting a Peace were to be set on foot between the Confederates and <hi>France,</hi> that ever so many States and Princes of the first rank in <hi>Christendom</hi> for true honour, brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and generosity would ever enter upon a Treaty, exclusive to a Prince whose fole conduct, personal Industry, and assistance has
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174132:11"/> contributed more to the curtailing that immoderate ambition of the <hi>French</hi> Tyrant, and settling an honourable and lasting Peace to <hi>Christendom,</hi> than any four of them together? But no less absurdities than these must go down glib with you, if you upon such frivolous encitements will expose your selves to these unnecessary evils: No, no, believe me, the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and unheard of practices of the <hi>French</hi> Monarch are not so easily to be compounded; the Confederates are too well acquainted with his Maxims, and trust me, will be as inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to his Hypocritical Proposals, as the Protestants here would be to any Remonstrances of King <hi>James:</hi> The open infractions of the Treaties of <hi>Aix la Chapelle</hi> and <hi>Nimeguen:</hi> The infamous and base surprizal of <hi>Strasbourg,</hi> even in a time of full Peace: The building of the Fort of <hi>Hunninghen,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his solemn Promises given to the <hi>Switzers,</hi> are too well remembered by the Confederates to give him the least prospect of a Peace, till returns suitable are made: His Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> since Eighty Two, and his unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressible Outrages committed upon the Empire, by attacking the Fort of <hi>Philipsbourg,</hi> even before any Declaration of War: His wasting the <hi>Palatinate</hi> with Fire and Sword with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the least cause or provocation: His unjust siezing, and basely detaining the Principality of <hi>Orange,</hi> King <hi>Williams</hi> Rightful Inheritance, and an hundred other Insolencies, Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries and Tragedies committed by him. As they have justly rendered him the Common Enemy of all the Catholick World, so you may be sure they have very meanly recommended him to all Protestants, and in particular to the <hi>English;</hi> and this is sufficient to convince you of your Folly and Madness in any wise relying on the assistance of <hi>France,</hi> who already begins, like a weary'd Gladiator, to lay by its Sword, the better to shield it self from the thickning blows of its vigorous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching Adversary.</p>
            <p>Since then, as I have plainly demonstrated your Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>France</hi> are so very inconsiderable; that as I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore evinced, you must incur the imputation of downright
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174132:12"/> Folly as well as Ingratitude, to engage your selves in such horrid attempts on so little encouragements: Let us in the next place consider the vanity of your relyance on the strength of the Army of <hi>Ireland</hi> for the reduction of King <hi>James:</hi> And here at first dash appears their cowardly and impolitick behaviour before the Walls of <hi>London-Derry;</hi> with such an awkard, uncouth look, as I assure you would strike an ill natur'd damp on any good Opinion I had conceived of them; believe me, it sounds but very gratingly in my Ears, when I hear and am convinced that so considerable a number of Men, and those the choice and flower of the whole <hi>Irish</hi> Nation, even under the Conduct of their fam'd <hi>French</hi> Leaders, and in their first attempt, and flush'd with the success of ravaging an unresisting Country before them; I say, it sounds very odly for these Men to see themselves, by the poor effects of the Garrison of one small Town, so repeatedly baffled, rout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and at last with the help of very small Supplies, utterly and with such precipitancy driven away, that for Forty Miles in length they hardly ventured to <hi>steal the Opportunity of look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back:</hi> That an Army, I say, of one grain of Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion should contentedly put up such a signal dishonour, is a strong Argument to me of putting very little assurance in their future Atchievments; but I know this is easily salv'd by our Friends with Apologies, as wholly inconsistent with Reason and never lying Interest, as that wretched and never to be forgotten Enterprize was with valour, and but tolerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. I know it is readily as insignificantly urg'd, that they never heeded formally to Besiege it; that King <hi>James</hi> his <hi>Mild Nature</hi> was willing to soften them into Obedience; that hang it, it was of little consequence if it had been taken; as the Countryman said of the Hare when he could not catch her; Arguments so silly and insipid, so full of absurdity and so undeserving of an Answer, that the Protestants laugh down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right at the non-sense of our evasions, and justly conclude us to be in the condition of drowning Men, who piteously catch at every straw to uphold them: Well, but I remember you
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174132:12"/> once objected to me one weighty Argument, (as you thought) and that was the necessity that press'd the <hi>Irish</hi> to the extremity of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and opposition from a just despair of obtaining any Reasonable Conditions, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Life, from so severely an enraged Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: To this I Answer, that notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the many Just Pretences King <hi>William</hi> may have utterly to destroy them, and root them entirely out of the Country; yet such is his known Generosity; known I say, even to all those of the better sort of the <hi>Irish</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it seems much more likely than impossible, that upon a small consideration and a good opportunity, they may much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incline to a moderate composition, than run the miserable hazard of their Lives, and the severities of a second Act of Settlement: They know how wretchedly they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready suffered by a vain fond opposition of an Enemy, who by all advantages in the World, must at all times, even by the vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of themselves, be acknowledged their Superiours, and upon pleasure able to reduce them to a Just Obedience; they have most
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174132:13"/> of them sowrly bit for their last pretensions of rising in Rebellion, and the Apothegme is too truly verified in them, that Plots dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, or Rebellions quash'd and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd, serve at all times to strengthen the hands of the Prince against whom they are design'd; and consequently, of putting it into his Power to determine their Fates ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Pleasure. If the <hi>Irish</hi> Army cannot drive out the <hi>English</hi> this Summer, you'll hardly find them in any tolerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition able to bring themselves into the Field another; their want of all Necessaries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be supplied from <hi>France,</hi> you'll Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably be satisfied of the extream difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they will have to keep together: Nay already, notwithstanding their boasted love to King <hi>James,</hi> they do with so much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence march, and prosecute any of their Officers Commands, that it is thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to buoy up their Hearts by fictitious stories of the Affairs of <hi>England:</hi> As that <hi>Scotland</hi> has declared, and stands out for King <hi>James:</hi> That there are considerable Risings in <hi>England</hi> for him: That the <hi>English</hi> Army
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174132:13"/> are weak, sick, and few in number: That King <hi>James</hi> expects nothing but the Fleet, who undoubtedly will come over to him, and then he shall be able to Transport him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self and his Army, and over-run all his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in the twinkling of an Eye; all meer stuff and banter; <hi>Chimaera's</hi> bred only in the doltish Brain of an <hi>Irish</hi> Politician, and which will serve to make their ruine more univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal; for let me tell you, this project of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the poor <hi>Irish,</hi> will in all probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be the greatest advance to the affairs of King <hi>William</hi> as may be; for when they shall be drawn out, as it were only to Plunder and Ravage a small body of weak Men, who already (as they are made believe) lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish with want of all Necessaries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and find unexpectedly, a vigorous, large, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>issant Army, in all things compleat; (for such really is King <hi>Williams</hi> Army in <hi>Ireland</hi>) the unexpected Surprize, their own Natural Cowardice, and the apprehensions of the Calamities they must of necessity expect from any Fruitless Resistance, will undoubtedly recollect their Senses, and very naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174132:14"/> them to hearken to any Conditions of Peace, rather than expose themselves afresh to the Arbitrary Determinations of an enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Prince, and conquering Army: But perhaps you will here object, and tell me, that I beg the question, and seem to swallow down suppositions, which by good assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances to the contrary you will not grant; you'll tell me that you doubt not of a brave demeanour, and in good probability you hope for the utter overthrow of the <hi>English</hi> Army this Summer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Well, but in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to all this, I will only tell you, that supposing the <hi>Irish</hi> Army will venture to look the <hi>English</hi> in the face, yet if a body by all Reasonable Circumstances may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude of a thing not actually done, you'll find but very little encouragement from their endeavours: For tell me, did they ever since the War begun, in any the least action, skirmish or assault, behave themselves with the least glimpse of Honour or Courage. The small Actions of <hi>Sligoe, Bellturbet, Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemont, Ballingargy, Dundalk,</hi> &amp;c. are such sure and reproachful marks of their future Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174132:14"/> that I should be every hour upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my peace with God, and preparing my self for a speedy remove, if my Life or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune depended upon their trivial assistance. And now dear Sir, I am very fond and apt to believe that I have evidently demonstrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you the unreasonableness of our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to raise War and Rebellion against King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> both from a respect of Honour and Gratitude due to the mild and bounteous Condescentions of the present Government to us; as also from the very little or no probability (if any possibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity) of succeeding, or attaining any the least end of such our horrid Insurrection and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: Which brings me to the last Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of the miserable consequences of such attempts, in case of failure; (which you have Fifty to One Reasons to fear:) I say, the sad effects, the Ruine, Slaughter, and Misery that will ensue to all the Roman Catholicks in <hi>England:</hi> You cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensible of the lamentable ruine and devasta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Houses, Chappels, and Persons, made by the Rabble in <hi>London,</hi> and else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:174132:15"/> about the time of the Princes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Town: At a time when the Roman Catholicks were in an entire subjection; when there could not be the least apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of danger from them, when they were in such a consternation, affright and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they might with all reason be much rather pity'd than fear'd; you saw that no Considerations, no Arguments, even from the moderate Protestants, could asswage their Fury, when all respect to all Quality was laid aside; when the very Houses of Forreign Ministers and Ambassadors were expos'd and ransack'd by an heedless strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed multitude; if such were then our fears, if such our dangers, if such their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteracy, and such our misery, what extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities shall we not have now reason to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, if by a weak essay, (for no other I think I have clearly evinc'd, and you will fatally find it to be) we lay a snare for our selves, into which if we fall, we may for ever justly despair of any redemption.</p>
            <p>Reflect, dear Friend, upon the reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableness of this Advice, and withdraw your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174132:15"/> foot e're you tread the dangerous toils. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that slighted or neglected Mercy commonly turns to the severest Vengeance; and think, we shall not have any more such Opportunities of making our selves easie and happy. Flatter not your self with the vain assurance of the number of your Associates; believe me, the main part of your assistance must be from <hi>Pick-Pockets, Cut-Throats, Pimps, Pandars, Hectours, Gamesters, Sharpers, and the like;</hi> for these sorts of People only are to his Eternal Reproach and our Grief, the Friends and Sticklers for King <hi>James:</hi> You must in your Conscience confess that these sorts of People were in great vogue at <hi>W—ll</hi> in the Two last Reigns, and that King <hi>James</hi> could never indeed hope to bring his projects to perfection, but by the assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of such Principled Persons; these only are the Male-Contents of <hi>England,</hi> (at least for the most part) and then judge by what Ability, Interest and Credit, they can pretend to sway the Country into a general resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of bringing back King <hi>James:</hi> Think not that the little grumbling of some unthinking
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:174132:16"/> People, who for the Necessary Imposition of a few Taxes, take a liberty of reflecting on the present Government, denotes a Disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to side with you for the restoring him; the People of <hi>England</hi> were ever a murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Generation on that score; however when the common safety comes to be seriously re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented, you'l find your hopes in them dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed: Popery and Slavery are the two Epidemical Grievances of the Nation; they have, like the Childrens Bug-Bears, in the very mention of them terrour; and believe me, in the opinion of the generality of the People, the very Name of King <hi>James</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes both.</p>
            <p>Remember well that it is not the business of private Men to dispute the Titles of Kings; and since the generality of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> of all Ranks and Degrees, by their Free Representatives in Parliament have thought fit to place King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> in the Throne, let not us who are not the Twentieth part of the People, and who by many positive Laws are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from any concern in the Government,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:174132:16"/> foolishly and madly pretend to opposition, and thereby give our ill-wishers, as well as the long-lull'd Justice of the Government, too fair an opportunity for our utter ruine and extirpation: Believe me my Friend, you cannot be so sensible of the inclination of the People from the scattering Discourses of a few Bigots in the Country, as I can from the constant Conversation of all sorts here; and let me tell you, it would prove but a very sorry provocative to Rebellion and rising in Arms, if you heard the unwelcome invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Protestants here as I do; who stick not upon all occasions publickly to wish for a discovery of the least Action of us, tending to a rising; and please themselves hugely with the thoughts of being entirely let loose at us: There's not a House, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or Person of the Romish Perswasion, but what they have already a shrewd eye upon; and believe me, upon the first News of any Insurrection would certainly have their hands. These will appear to you surely dreadful Considerations, to see the Papists on all hands, both innocent and guilty, indistinctly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174132:17"/> fall Sacrifices both in their Lives and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, to a blind, impartial, popular Rage; and whoever should have the fortune to es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape that, would however lye obnoxious to the Inquisition of the Government; and at least, by fresh Laws be justly ty'd up from all those Liberties which by Natural Right are the Just Claims, Enjoyments and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness of every true <hi>English-Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus, my dear Friend, I have shewn you the two great Paths of Good and Evil, of Peace and War, of Dutiful Submission and Wicked Rebellion. I have laid before you the inconveniencies of the one, and the satisfactions of the other; have abstracted the Englishman from the Papist, the Subject from the Male-Content: I have satisfied you of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of Obedience to the Present Government, and the dire Consequences of Resistance. A right Application of what has been said to you, will be all the returns I can wish from you, and which will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways preserve to you the value and esteem of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Faithful Friend <hi>J. G.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:174132:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>